# Amy X. Lu

http://amyxlu.github.io github.com/amyxlu amyxlu@stanford.edu +1-650-776-6772 linkedin.com/in/amyxlu

#### Summary

I am a graduate student at the Vector Institute for Artificial Intelligence. I am interested in **developing** biologically-principled machine learning methods, with an emphasis on self-supervised representation learning, generalizability, and biological interpretability. I also serve on SVAI, which organizes research collaborations of genomics/AI researchers and industry partners for patients of understudied diseases.

#### EDUCATION

University of Waterloo
Bachelors of Science, Honours Science, Bioinformatics Option
2014 - 2019
University of Toronto, Vector Institute
Master's Degree in Computer Science
Stanford University
Partial completion of Master's Thesis, Departments of Computer Science and Genetics
Sept 2019 - Present

#### EXPERIENCE

## Stanford University

Palo Alto, USA

Visiting Student Researcher — Domain Adaptation in Regulatory Genomics, Dr. Anshul Kundaje

2019 - Present

• Domain adaptation, ChIP-seq analyses: Using domain adaptation to improve classifier performance and learned genomic sequence features for transcription factor binding when evaluating in a different cellular context.

## University of Toronto/Vector Institute

Toronto, Canada

Masters Student — Representation learning in genomics, Dr. Alan Moses & Dr. Marzyeh Ghassemi 2019 – Present

- Self-supervised learning, natural language processing: Applying contextual word embedding models to learn generalizable and interpretable representations for genomic and proteomic sequences.
- o Generalizability, computer vision: Benchmarked a new "paired cell in-painting" method for out-of-sample generalization in microscopy against various common computer vision algorithms. (NeurIPS 2019 21% acceptance rate; ICML 2019 Self-Supervised Learning Workshop)
- o Algorithmic fairness, clinical decision support: Quantitative and qualitative evaluation of bias in "black box" contextual clinical word embeddings, and exploring debiasing methods using adversarial gradient-reversal. (NeurIPS 2019 ML for Healthcare workshop 34% acceptance rate; submitted to FAT\* 2020)

#### Harvard Medical School/Boston Children's Hospital

Boston, USA

Research Intern — Machine Learning in Clinical Genomics, Dr. Piotr Sliz

2018 - 2019

- Variant analysis, denoising, genotype-phenotype studies: Applied false-positive variant filtering pipelines and batch effect denoising algorithms to a whole exome (WES) dataset of epilepsy patients.
- Machine learning, dimensionality reduction: Built machine learning models to classify disease phenotype from high-dimensional exome variant data, with emphasis on capturing non-linearities arising from epistasis.

#### University of Waterloo

Waterloo, Canada

Undergraduate Thesis Student — Deep Learning in Regulatory Genomics, Dr. Andrew Doxey

2017 - 2018

- $\circ$  Convolutional neural networks in genomics: Implemented a convolutional neural network which recognizes genomic enhancers regulating femur growth with 91% accuracy.
- Interpretability: Distilled biological knowledge from the "black box" network by reconstructing first-layer features as position-weighted matrices (PWMs) of "motifs" (i.e. genomic patterns). All motifs found statistical matches in JASPAR (database of known motifs).
- Phylogenetics, metagenomic data mining: Used various bioinformatics pipeline tools (HMMER, BLAST, etc.) to understand and discover potential novel toxin homologs in metagenomic databases.
- $\circ\,$  Self-directed learning: Self-learned deep learning concepts and Python as a biology student.

## École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne

Lausanne, Switzerland

Research Intern — Structural Biology and MD Simulations, Dr. Matteo Dal Parero

- Molecular dynamics: Contributed three potential findings on enzyme-membrane mechanisms of bacterial "superbugs" using computational molecular dynamics (MD) simulations.
- Automating workflows: Automated workflows and analyzed simulations using R, tcl/tk, and Csh scripts.

#### University of Toronto

Toronto, Canada

Research Intern — Data Visualization in Pharmacoepidemiology, Dr. Suzanne Cadarette

2015 - 2017

- **Pharmacoepidemiology:** Took initiative to redesign manual workflows. Contributed two co-authored publications, one poster, and figures for an international epidemiology conference within two months.
- o Data visualization: Wrangled data using R and SQL to create animated and interactive co-authorship networks.

#### AWARDS

- NSERC Michael Smith Foreign Supplement: Supports high-calibre Canadian graduate students in pursuing research abroad. Valued at \$6,000.
- Canada Graduate Scholarships-Master's (CGS-M) Award: NSERC federal research grant. Valued at \$17,500.
- Scholarship of Excellence in Research: One of 13 students sponsored for research at EPFL. Valued at CHF 4,500.
- University of Waterloo: Various entrance awards totaling \$6,000.
- Associate of The Royal Conservatory (ARCT): Performer's Diploma in Piano.

#### Publications and Conference Proceedings

- Accepted: Lu AX, Lu AXP, Moses A. The Cells Out of Sample (COOS) dataset and benchmarks for measuring out-of-sample generalization of image classifiers. *Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems* (NeurIPS) 2019.
- Submitted: Zhang H\*, Lu AX\*, Abdalla M, McDermott M, Ghassemi M. Hurtful Words: Quantifying Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Submitted to ACM Conference on Fairness, Accountability, and Transparency (ACM FAT\*). \*Co-first authors.
- Published: Ban J, Tadrous M, Lu AX, Cicinelli EA, Cadarette SM. Diffusion of indirect comparison meta-analytic methods to study drugs: a systematic review and co-authorship network analysis. *BMJ Open*.
- Under revision: Consiglio GP, Maclure M, Lu AX, Cicinelli EA, Ban JK, McCarthy L, Cadarette SM. Guidance documents for the application of Self-controlled Crossover Observational PharmacoEpidemiology (SCOPE) designs are needed: systematic review and animated co-authorship networks. Submitted to Pharmcoepi Drug Saf.

#### Workshop Papers and Poster Presentations

- Accepted: Lu AX\*, Zhang H\*, Abdalla M, McDermott M, Ghassemi M. Hurtful Words: Quantifying Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Hurtful Words: Quantifying Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Poster presentation, NeurIPS 2019 Workshop on Fair ML for Health. \*Co-first authors.
- Accepted: Zhang H\*, Lu AX\*, Abdalla M, McDermott M, Ghassemi M. Hurtful Words: Quantifying Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Hurtful Words: Quantifying Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Extended Abstract, NeurIPS 2019 Workshop on Machine Learning for Healthcare. \*Co-first authors.
- Accepted: Abdalla M, Lu AX, Zhang H, Chen I, Ghassemi M. Quantifying Fairness in a Multi-Group Setting and its Impact in the Clinical Setting. Poster presentation, NeurIPS 2019 Workshop on Fair ML for Health.
- Submitted: Moses A, Lu AX, Lu AXP, Ghassemi M. Transfer Learning vs. Batch Effects: what can we expect from neural networks in computational biology?. *Machine Learning in Computational Biology (MLCB) 2019*.
- Presented: Lu AX, Lu AXP, Moses A. Paired Cell Inpainting: A Multiple-Instance Extension of Self-Supervised Learning for Bioimage Analysis. *Poster presentation, ICML 2019 Workshop on Self-Supervised Learning.*
- Presented: Lu AX, Rockowitz S, Poduri A, Sliz P. From data to precision medicine: predictive machine learning models to uncover disease-associated variants. Poster and "Lightning Talk". Harvard Medical School BCMP Retreat 2019.
- Submitted: Lu AX, Tam ES. Effect of prophylactic brimonidine on subconjunctival hemorrhage in laser-assisted cataract surgery. Poster abstract. Submitted to American Academy of Ophthalmology 2017.
- Presented: Lu AX, Consiglio GP, Cadarette SM. Dynamic Visualization in Co-Authorship Network Analysis. Poster presentation. Leslie Dan Faculty of Pharmacy Undergraduate Research Symposium.
- Presented: McIlroy-Young R, Lu AX, Guenther N, Olarnyk A. A Network Analysis: Did the Arab Spring Impact the Academic Network of Tunisia Between 2010 and 2015? Poster presentation. Knowledge Integration Symposium.

## SERVICE AND ACTIVITIES

- SVAI: Core Team of SVAI, a non-profit connecting patients of rare genomic diseases to the medical/AI research community and industry partners through collaborative research initiatives.
- Residence Don, Velocity Incubator: Leader for the residence program of Canada's most productive start-up incubator; fostered close relations with diverse students to support conduct and mental health crises.
- Tosamaganga Hospital, Tanzania: Supported operations at a rural Tanzanian hospital and shadowed surgical procedures. Expenses were covered by scholarships, fundraising, and part-time tutoring.

#### Teaching

- Teaching Assistant, Genetics: Taught weekly tutorials for BIOL 239 at the University of Waterloo.
- Piano & theory: Taught piano performance (up to RCM 7), RCM music history, and RCM Intermediate Rudiments.
- Tutoring: Tutor for IB Calculus, IB Chemistry, and English.

## HACKATHONS AND PROJECTS

- Chatsense: Mobile chat app using a sentiment analysis machine learning API on voice messages and mapping dominant emotions to emojis, designed for the autistic community. Team project. "Can a Computer Hear How You Feel?" prize: YHacks at Yale.
- Alice: Web login page using a trained facial recognition model to login to online banking without passwords, designed for dementia patients. *Team project. Desjardin prize: ConUHacks III.*